Hi, I'm Sandra from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 10 of our 10-day Lip reading Challenge,
designed to help you develop
and practice your speech reading skills!
Hearing loss can have a
profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career,
your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and tricks
on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity
to relationships in all areas of your life.
I have so enjoyed creating this challenge for you.
I hope you've learned a lot and had fun too.
Your surprise for today is a Quiz.
This will give you a really good idea
of how much you've learned.
Details are below, and the answers are provided.
Through the last nine days
of the challenge,
you've learned
the most visible sounds in English.
We learned about these most visible sounds
in homophene groups,
where we could.
Homophene groups are groups of sounds that look alike
on the lips.
So the homophene groups
that we learned about are P, B, and M;
F and V;
and SH, CH, and J.
We also learned about the W sound,
the TH sound, and all about vowels.
Just as sounds can look alike,
words can look alike too.
Words that look the same
on the lips are called homophenous words,
and that's what we're going to practice today.
For example, take the word roam.
There are three words that look like roam.
What are they?
Substitute the M for P or a B,
and consider alternate spellings.
If you're not sure,
the answers are written below.
Pause the video now
and write down the four words:
roam plus the three homophenous words.
I will say sentences silently
with these four words.
I'll give you some photos
for some context,
but hold on to the images
lightly in your mind and stay flexible.
We get into trouble
when we hold on to things like terriers.
Are you ready?
I'm going to say each sentence twice.
Number 1
And here it is again:
Number 2
Here's number two again:
Number 3
And number 3 again:
Number 4
Here's number 4 again:
Okay, let's move on
to a new group of words.
There are two words
that look like the word hear.
Consider that the H is invisible,
and remember alternate spellings.
Pause the video now,
and write down the three words:
hear plus the two homophenous words.
Are you ready?
I'll say each sentence twice.
Number 5
Here's number 5 again:
Number 6
Here's Number 6 again:
and Number 7
Number 7 again:
For the last three sentences,
there are two words
that look exactly the same on the lips.
Watch me and find the matching pair.
Number 8
Here it is again:
Number 9
Number 9 again:
and Number 10
Number 10 again:
Okay, that's it for
our lip reading practice today.
Don't forget to take the quiz below.
I hope this was useful to you
and that you had fun too.
There's lots more to learn so maybe you'll take an online class
or two.
I'd be honored to have the opportunity to teach you.
Many people with hearing loss do their best
to avoid group listening situations,
especially if there's going to be people that they're unfamiliar with.
And I would count myself in that category.
Here's a photo of me in my 20s
at a family reunion.
Our family reunions were very noisy.
And this is my cousin.
And I remember this moment,
because I was totally faking it.
I couldn't hear most of what
he was saying
and I didn't tell him.
That was my go-to strategy—bluffing—at
that time. That was before I had
my cochlear implant.
In our group classes,
we talk about communication strategies,
and we discuss bluffing
because it is a communication strategy.
And we talk about the merits of it,
and some drawbacks.
And I find that it's an opportunity
to reflect a little bit more deeply,
even for my own learning.
However in the hundreds of hours
that I've spent teaching
people with hearing loss to read lips,
there's one thing
that doesn't change from class to class.
I'm always astounded by
the power of being with
other people who understand
The power of being understood.
I invite you to try.
That said, if a group class just is just not for you,
I have suggestions for other ways to keep going.
I've written them below. Check it out!
As always, please like, subscribe, and share with others.
Take care!